we were speaking
this morning about
what meditation is and
as i i said that to me it was about
cleaning the mind
but again that's not
that needs qualification you know
describing what does that mean what is
that all about
and you're saying
that it's simply a kind of relaxation
calm calming yourself calming down calming down
yeah
calming the mind
like in in broadest
in broadest terms somebody who doesn't
know what meditation is has no notion of
any techniques anything
if they were to ask what is what is
meditation
to convey them you know without becoming
going technical or something
just however it's a way of of calming
your mind
so when the mind needs calming you calm
it down
so if i'm agitated
anyone can yeah
most people can get agitated
and you need to calm down what do you do
that's the whole that's kind of the
whole point because
learning how to calm your mind down
skillfully without involving centrality or
without involving centrality or
distraction
that's that's the the wisdom that's the
work that's the value of it so most
people will just calm their mind
by the means of centrality by the means
of seeking pleasure
and that's what the world said in the
sutras when touched by unpleasant
feeling an untrained mind the only
escape that they know from that pain
is uh sensual pleasure
so they would seek sensuality
to pretty much pacify their mind so the
mind comes down in regard to something
else that bothered them
so in other words
pretty much just replacing
covering up you know
pasting a cover on the wound that you don't want
a cover on the wound that you don't want
to deal with
just some nice cooling patch or
something but underneath it's still the same wound
but underneath it's still the same wound
so that's the difference between like um
doing meditation for the right reason
intermediate for the wrong reason
like are you doing meditation just to
get away from stuff
to not deal with the things
or to just calm your mind in regard to
things that are still there
that are otherwise agitating you
where am i trying to replace
yeah replace them exactly am i trying to
basically avoid the pain
or am i trying to count my mind in
regard to the pain
and not trying to get rid of it that's
the fundamental difference there
and and that's why it's important like what
and that's why it's important like what
view person carries
in regard to meditation
see most of the contemporary meditation
notions even if people have genuine
reasons when you say meditation it's immediate
when you say meditation it's immediate
kind of implication of a
special super
pleasant experience
that you get if you do a technique if
you're committed to it this pleasure
overwhelms you and you had a very
successful meditation
but that's that's not necessarily calming to
that's that's not necessarily calming to
begin with and second it's kind of
exactly the same principle as sensuality
is
oh i'm bothered by things
let me make let me do some work let me
earn let me gain so that i can enjoy
this vast amount of pleasures they will calm
vast amount of pleasures they will calm
me down and make me very satisfied
so sometimes people realize that
sensuality will not necessarily provide
that or cannot then it turns to
meditation but they don't change the
attitude so there's the whole idea of like john
so there's the whole idea of like john
as being this pleasure that overwhelms
you and it's ecstatic and you can't even
have enough of it and stuff it's a
complete just uh just the replacement of
same views of centrality just replacing
the objects that you usually chase
because that's that's what's in people's
mind that expectation of i'm doing this
when will this pleasure overwhelm me
when will it happen
and would you consider yourself calming
yourself down if you're cultivating
expectations like is he's expecting things is that a
like is he's expecting things is that a
calming state of mind
anticipation is that a calming
quality no not at all
no not at all
how many people can say they can truly
meditate without the slightest view of
anticipation contemporarily like when they come
contemporarily like when they come
across meditation buddhist or otherwise
it's it's implicit
what's happening looking what's
happening so that you can interpret
what's happening waiting for things to
happen hoping they will happen
again meditating with centrality
waiting for things to happen they will
be pleasant they will solve everything
else out no
you didn't suit this summertime it's
calming your mind
not getting rid of things that disturb
the mind
getting rid of things that they
distribute through restraint but then
when the mind is agitated on its own
account and a kind of ignorance on a
kind of not
having not a brutal greed aversion
distraction you can't just get those things out of
you can't just get those things out of
your mind because that's what your mind
is
so then you need to learn as we said
before how to calm yourself down within that
how to calm yourself down within that
endurance
but you will never begin
um going in that right direction of
calming for as long as you don't
relinquish your views of meditation
bringing this pleasure
meditation ignoring of what the mind is
with china yeah exactly i'm just trying
to get a pleasant experience instead of
this unpleasant experience that's
exactly the puttugena's way
when touched by pain he only the only
escape he knows is seeking pleasure
it doesn't matter whether he seeks
pleasure through
food company others or meditation
he seeks pleasure because he doesn't
want to deal with pain
and that's why it's a central view that
underlines that meditation any
meditation of that kind
so yeah it reminds me that that
kanti paraman
is the highest austerity the patient
endurance which is the highest highest
practice eyes that's the meditation
that's the meditation yeah
so it's not about replacing the
experience that has arisen
it's about thoroughly knowing it while
it's there
but in order to the point will come
where in order to fully understand it
you need to learn how to stay calm
within it
and that's the role of the proper
samadhi that's where the right view is
the necessary basis for the right
samadhi because the right view will know that
because the right view will know that
well no it's about enduring disorder
mind is disturbed because the mind is
not free
but if i just seek to replace it with
pleasurable experience i haven't
understood what needs to be understood
so what if i instead seek to calm it
within the disturbing experience within
the agitated mind i learned how to calm
myself within that
and then the agitation disappears and
that with agitated you're still there
and you get to understand it now because
the mind sees clearly when it's calm
and that's the pleasure that willa talks
about the pleasure that's different the
pleasure of sensuality pleasure of not
being bothered pleasure of being
withdrawn pleasure since you strained
it's a it's a pleasure that you called
you that's pretty much yeah yeah
it's a it's a it's a pleasure that you
cannot crave for more
because it didn't come in that external
sense of just a replacement just
something that overwhelms you
so and even the pleasure of jhana it's
the pleasure of that withdrawal from
beforehand that's what the pleasure
belongs to not to vagina
having been secluded he experienced the
pleasure of seclusion
and then his mind becomes confident in
that and then he basically is abiding in
china as a result of that seclusion and
as a result of that seclusion and
non-activity that we spoke
before because that's truly what is
disturbing
it's the movements of the mind you can't
you can't calm it
so you seeking pleasure is just another
movement that's a fundamental exactly another
that's a fundamental exactly another
expectation and that anticipation even
if you get it if you don't get it
doesn't matter
you are still relying on the perpetual
movement of the mind
um to remain floating so to speak and
that's not peaceful
that's not calming even if you get all
the pleasure you want in the world
so the true summit of then is calming
of those movements of those activities
those cincadas
intentions of the mind calming that within whatever
of the mind calming that within whatever
you're intending
towards or against
but in order to calm your your
intentions on the mental level you need
to have calmed your body you need to
have common speech you need to have
restrain it sufficiently long before
that's where jhana begins with your
keeping the virtue pretty much
that's already calming
stealing of the activities as the buddha
would say stealing of the cincadas it's
not magical about it
he's just there is intention to move you
don't necessarily move
through that intention you see where
it's rooted is it intentionally rooted
in agitation
then you endure it then you try to not
get rid of the agitation but remove
intention to move in the face of
agitation but that's quite subtle already
but that's quite subtle already
but if somebody has been thoroughly
withdrawn physically physically
verbally
not delighting in company living in
seclusion yet that would be a very
visible thing
you see why you suffer not because there
is the disturbing thought
it's because the mind
feels confined by it and wants to get
rid of it
and that's the root of suffering
that movements of that craving not what
has arisen
but you need to you need to have been
been thoroughly strained and withdrawn
and then you can actually even start
calming that movement of the mind
not at the expense of what
what is
agitating you
that remains that actually serves almost
as a criteria
whether you calm now or not because it's
easy to become when there's nothing
bothering you
but why do people don't want to live in
why do people don't want to live in
seclusion
uh avoid
not not by taking company not practice
sense restraining god descends those
because it's very disturbing
you start saying no to sensuality god in
the sense those avoiding company living
alone it's very disturbing for the mind
because it's used to that well exactly
because it depends on the movements yeah
that's the the life is defined by the
movements by activities by engagements
by intention
when you sit still so to speak
mentally you know you try to calm down
just you sit still yes it's still you
you then are faced
or you've you faced with that whole
flow of where you the mind's the
direction their mind yeah sure sure you
feel the the pressure of its direction
so you want to you want to sit still you
want to feel the pressure
but then you don't want to distract
yourself from that mental side of it so
then you realize yeah you can walk up
and down you can move around
but none of the bodily actions should be
rooted in that vegetation that you want
to get rid of
so if you're just pacing up and down
it's not it's not really the activity
that's connected to the activity of the
mind that wants to avoid things that are
agitating it that's why that's why the gradual
it that's why that's why the gradual
training is about building that up
because that is the most disturbing
thing solitude seclusion withdrawal from the
solitude seclusion withdrawal from the
senses confinement
it's it basically feels like dying it
feels like a withdrawal of a heavy
addict addict who's been depending on the
addict who's been depending on the
senses
for even not just in this life
so and that's why it's not optional
really it's just more like whether
you're gonna take it seriously and work
towards it
or you're gonna develop the view that
will kind of
convince you that you're exempted from
it because you know you can just sit in
your room for half an hour
going to some state of concentration and
think you're somehow doing the work by
being unaware
yeah that's where gradual training naturally
that's where gradual training naturally
results in jhana
it is trained by the virtue moderate in
eating watchful wakeful
guarding the sense those minds withdraw
and be drawn and withdrawn seclusion
and then he enters and lives in the
future
which is basically learning how to live
apart from the dependence on the
pleasure of the senses and for that you
need to have been withdrawn sufficiently
because an addict
an addict
who is trying to give up
whatever cigarettes
then you go through this these
withdrawal symptoms symptoms
but
you know difficult whatever week a month
whatever it is
you agitate it and so on
and then
you're okay
but sometimes it gets people trying to
replace that with something else sure
well because it's a relative addiction
but we're not talking about one
particular thing that you're addicted
through your senses
to motherhood's answers yeah so if you
think cigarettes are hard to give up a
heroin well yeah you'll see if you try
giving up the actual pleasure depending
on the senses in existence in general
but that is the way out
that is the way up that's why it is the
way out but you understand that small
little you get a glimpse sure a glimpse of i'm
you get a glimpse sure a glimpse of i'm
i'm now not agitated exactly
by being withdrawn from this and this so
you can imagine that the pleasure even
with the first genre
when you're not drawn by anything in the
world you're not undermining addicted by the
you're not undermining addicted by the
sense no addiction
you were you were completely
dry off it and even if you have the
thoughts they are not central thoughts
like before you know the ones that would
immediately pressure
and that's a true release laying down of
the burden
but there is no magical way
you know watch your left nostril watch
your right three steps left turn around
do this do that no the withdrawal from
that which you're addicted to that is
the magical way
and you need to give your drone
sufficient how long well that depends how strong
how long well that depends how strong
your addiction was
again every time
what is the meditation that the lord
praises the buddha praises well it's
this meditation here i say come before
we'll restrain with patimoca be moderate
in eating be watchful karcher sends
those quickly live in
live in
seclusion don't don't don't engage in
company and you'll enter in the body in the
and you'll enter in the body in the
first john that's the meditation that
lord approves
that's it that's the technique
technique of basically overcoming the
addiction of the addictions the
addiction of the senses
without replacements and by the way yeah
that's how people can replace it
you know through strong determination
committing to something else committing
to even more activity constant work
perpetual distraction company can keep
you like your mind away from seeking
core sensuality but you're not uprooting
anything that's just like a herring
addict finding something else
to keep his mind addicted to that's not
dealing with it it's not free from
addiction no no no because the moment
those activities become
unavailable his resting spot of his mind is where
his resting spot of his mind is where
his addiction still is so he'll go back
to that which he hasn't uprooted
so that's what meditation is
once you have basically
sufficiently wholesomely disturbed your
mind by unwavering sense restraint and
by unwavering sense restraint and
guarding of the sense doors
seclusion now you learn how to calm within that
now you learn how to calm within that
not abandon it
but calm
still the agitation aspect of it
so that you can carry on because you're
realizing already
that that's the way out but how how do
you still
the agitated aspect well
if i tell you how to do it there will be
another activity you're going to do
so the only way to do it is to endure it
and through that endurance when you have
no room to move left right forward or
backward you will find a way out to calm yourself
you will find a way out to calm yourself
down
and how would that be by not moving left
right forward or backward that's what
you should do
how the master got him across the shore
then by not fighting the waves by not pulling
by not fighting the waves by not pulling
backward by not standing still that's
what i did
so if you're pushing forward don't
pulling backward dogs standing still
don't but but
those
activities movements will become a
pattern if you have been sufficiently
restrained and lived withdrawn
and that's also why often in this i mean
i said it many times probably but
it's not it's not you can't accidentally
become enlightened who will accidentally
become free from addiction through
enduring the pain of withdrawal for six
months without without a reason without
a determining goal to go through that
who who would accidentally just choose
to
do that perpetually for so long that
they actually become free no there has
to be
some knowledge some some
some will behind
to commit to their training to see some
benefit in it peace nibbana exactly just
that idea of
ultimate the ultimate the highest thing that i
the ultimate the highest thing that i
attain is that complete peace
and that's why people when they when
they did you know people they were not
restrained or interested in practice
they encountered the buddha when and
they insisted to know what he's teaching
and when he would describe an ibana to
them they would be shocked and say well
that's death
kill me
yeah that will kill me that will destroy
what i am because it will because
whatever people are is what it's based
on the senses and sense pleasures
yes as we said in in the past why
is it difficult to give up
cigarettes because that is your whole
world your world
that you are yeah so it would be like
and again cigarettes heroin alcohol all
those particular addictions within
sensuality now you're giving up
basically pleasure of the senses
pleasure of the activity through the
senses so the only way to do that successfully
so the only way to do that successfully
is gradual training
have a wide base
of of unshakable virtue
wide base of sense restraint moderation
in eating watchfulness
wide base of guarding the sensors
so then like you know all the struggle
that you your mind will go through for
withdrawals you can come within that
without sort of falling off that base
that's the boundary there that you can
yeah that's why i said like you know
it's it's actually from the point of
view of developing your mind it's better
because people something to ask
oh well you know okay i understand i
want to meditate but i understand how to
keep the precepts in order to meditate
again first well why do you want to
meditate specifically
you're saying yes meditation itself is a
goal while you're still seeking pleasure
while you're still seeking pleasure
but then second okay so you want to keep
the preset so do keep five or eight or
what when how long
it's actually better if
oh should i keep eight presets you know
once a week or something
it's better to keep the five presets but
once you take them you take them for the
rest of your life
not for two days five years
that becomes that wide base i'm talking
about has to be done in that sense
you know a healing addict will not free
himself if he goes to rehab on the
weekends and then he's back to the world
and then he's back to the world
he's just
silly so
so
take on the five precepts
forever that already is going to be confinement
that already is going to be confinement
for the mind of addiction or sensuality
that's already oh okay and that's the
weight you need to start taking on in
that gradual training that's the whole
point like even even when
when the chant is recite when they
recite the four paragraphs
for grave offenses if you commit you're
not amongst that and then he says what
those things are it's not to be done for
the rest of your life by you
it's just
not like it's it has to be taken in the
ultimate sense so it's better to even
take like just five precepts
but in an ultimate sense and that's what
the all the late followers and the
suitors did
i go to the refuge for the rest of my
life let buddha know me as a late
follower means this now is the basis
means this now is the basis
of my
that sensory strain confinement to 536
which is very
easy
it's not even confining confining so
but as i said
take that in the ultimate sense and then
on top of that if sometimes you want to
keep the 836 yes
but when you don't keep the eight
precepts there is no falling lower than
the five precepts that is your basis
they must remain your basis
and then if you really feel no no i do
really want to free myself once and for
all or or at least make an attempt for
it then you take the eight presets
for the rest of your life
you take up that basis in the ultimate
sense of eight precepts
that's it through that
because now that's something you must
protect oh
oh
you're forced to be mindful
you're forced to be moderate and not
overdo things they will make you spill
out of and break the precepts
well you are forced to watch your senses
guard them because if you don't it
becomes very unpleasant within the
confinement of their precepts and the
mind that wants to do that which is
outside of the eight presets
and that's how you start taming it
and all the similarities in the sutures
you know get a wild elephant from the
forest from the jungle where he was just
roaming around
strap it down with big you know
peg and leather straps
and then wait for it to calm down
because he's just gonna
it comes down then
loosen up a bit move it left move it
right okay train it feed it
until until it starts to until it starts
to accept it
and yeah that's that's the mind
it's not going to do what you feel like
no you are going against the entire
grain of samsara of existence
you know just seeking one pleasant
experience to replace the other one
you're uprooting all of it
so that's meditation
calming amidst that withdrawing
withdrawing
calming well withdrawal
the wild mind still kicks and screams
you're calming it without abandoning the
drawer without giving into the senses
without giving into the senses
without letting the elephant go back to
the to the jungle to ease itself to have a
to the jungle to ease itself to have a
break yeah no no
there is no going back
non-return
exactly one of abandons ensure he's not
coming back to this world impossible
for that very reason
he has abandoned dependence on anything
from this world
it's not a poetic name of non-returning
factual
he's never returning to any
of the previous addictions he won't be
returning no he cannot he's been
abandoned no matter what happens no
matter what happens
inconceivable like a stone split in half cannot be
like a stone split in half cannot be
joined together
with a dry leaf can it become green
again yeah just irreversible
yeah just irreversible
if you if you accomplish the grain
against the samsara it's irreversible
you cannot go back down and impossible
that's why free mind is known as oh it's
free
success uh an addict an alcoholic would
be like
not drinking for 10 years but can they
still go back
well yeah because they haven't uploaded
their centrality yeah they're not
non-returners no exactly
kind of but in a way yeah like
many of them would not like
even i think even in that sense you can
get a glimpse because once you like with
cigarettes for example you free yourself
from that addiction
and you go back to cigarettes and it's
sickening so it will take work now
so it will take work now
to work through to become addicted again
and and it's kind of impossible for you
to go through that work carelessly
knowing what you've been through
when you truly freely uh freed yourself
from the addiction of it and there's
nothing that it actually offers you
no
no no it was a simple carelessness and
independence and pleasure unchecked
dependence and pleasure that people
become addicted to stuff so
but having fully approved the sensuality
fully understood the extent of the
danger of it is just impossible for mine
to even entertain that as a possibility
anymore that elephant you dragged out of the
that elephant you dragged out of the
forest to tame it has finally understood
seen for himself
you don't need to tell it anymore
the pedal of going back there
and then
you can you can unhook it you can remove
all the straps it will not go back there
because it was actually unpleasant
always was and again that's what the
buddha described for centrality
it's like the leper burning with embers
finding pleasure in burning his wounds
yeah but because of his condition that
burning relieves him of the pain of his
wounds so it feels pleasant
but burning of the embers in itself it
always always was unpleasant so it's
only relatively pleasant centrality
because of your mental condition
addiction dependence scratching the age
so once
the laptop is free
from that skin condition would he even
consider burning himself again
it was immense pain
just unbearable pain
because the reason that was providing
that relative pleasure is gone
so it just becomes inconceivable for him
to do that
madness yes you see that it's a madness yeah
yes you see that it's a madness yeah
absolute illness